地          球          脉          动
这是我们地球上的温室-丛林
This is our planet's hothouse. The jungle.
即热带雨林
The tropical rainforest.
雨林虽然仅占陆地的百分之三
Forests like these occupy only three percent of the land
却汇集了世界上一半以上的物种.
yet they're home to over half of the world's species.
那么如此众多的动植物种类 是如何获得自己的生存空间的呢?
But how do so many different kinds of plants and animals find the space here to live alongside one another?
富    饶    丛    林
画 外 音
大卫 · 爱登堡   爵士
在幽暗的森林地表上
On the dark, humid forest floor
看上去毫无生气
the jungle appears to be lifeless.
只听到各种生物的鸣叫
Often the only signs of life are what you hear.
这只雄性蓝极乐鸟正在做征婚广告
A male blue bird of paradise is advertising for a mate.
它的表演很精彩, 不过它并不是唯一给人深刻印象的极乐鸟
It's quite a performance but he's not the only bird of paradise here keen to make an impression.
在巴布亚新几内亚岛上大约有40种不同种类的极乐鸟
There are nearly forty different kinds on the island of New Guinea
每一种都有令人惊异的外表
each with a display seemingly more bizarre than the rest.
来福枪极乐鸟
A riflebird of paradise.
像其他的丛林动物一样,极乐鸟也尽量避免相互竞争
Like many jungle animals, birds of paradise avoid competing with each other
因此,它们生活在这个丛林岛屿的不同地方
and these do so by living in different parts of this jungle covered island.
六羽极乐鸟正在它的森林地表的舞台上跳独特的舞步
The six plumed bird of paradise displays in his special clearing, on the forest floor.
华丽极乐鸟喜欢呆在低矮的灌木丛上
The magnificent bird of paradise favors the low branches of bushes.
雌鸟却穿着朴素的衣服
His female is modestly dressed.
雄华丽极乐鸟有着嘹亮的歌声
The male has a good set of lungs
但要给雌鸟留下好印象的话它还需要加倍的努力
but he'll have to do more than flutter his eyelids, if he wants to impress her.
全依赖于它的表演
It'll all depend on his performance.
雌鸟满是怀疑地看着它因为她非常挑剔
The females may be dull looking but they're very picky
不过这次她已经准备好了亲密接触
and it's time for a really close inspection.
他的右边看上去不错,左边呢?
His right side looks fine... but what about his left?
印象非常深刻,他够不够华丽呢?
Pretty impressive, but is he magnificent enough?
哦,天
Oh dear.
她的离去说明了一切
Her departure says it all.
一代代追求异性的动力 促使他们进化出了不平凡的外表
Generations of choosy females have driven the evolution of these remarkable displays.
越是与众不同就越能引起注意
The more extravagant a male is, the more likely he'll be noticed.
新几内亚岛地处热带,赤道从岛中穿过
New Guinea lies in a warm tropical belt that girdles our planet around the equator.
大量的降雨和每天12小时的日照
With abundant rainfall and twelve hours of daylight
一年365天天天如此,造就了这里茂密的雨林
three hundred and sixty five days a year, it's here that rainforests flourish.
只有百分之二的阳光能够照射到雨林的地表上
Surprisingly only two percent of the sunlight filters down to the forest floor.
在这里,秧苗奋力向上生长
Down here seedlings struggle to grow
只为摆脱黑暗束缚
but the gloom is not eternal.
雨林中树木的死亡虽然令人伤感
The death of a forest giant is always sading
但若保持雨林的健康这种事情必须要发生.
but it has to happen if the forest is to remain healthy.
太阳一瞬间的光辉也能给森林地表带来生命
The sudden blaze of sunlight will bring life to the forest floor.
一公顷雨林就可以容纳250种不同的树木
A single hectare of rainforest may contain as many as 250 species of tree.
为英国的10倍
That's nearly ten times the number that grow in Britain
对阳光的渴望引发了这场生长竞赛
and the thirst for light triggers a race for a place in the sun.
没有时间去浪费
There's no time to waste.
几天前才落下的种子突然破土而出
A seed that may have fallen only a few days ago, now bursts through the leaf litter.
在这么多的竞争者面前 有一个好的开始非常重要
With so many competitors, getting a good start is critical
在这个难得的机会面前 每种植物都有自己非常独特的生长方式
but each plant has it's own particular strategy for making the most of this rare opportunity.
阔叶木发芽速度虽然不慢
The seeds of hardwoods are quick to germinate
不过它们的策略还是稳扎稳打
but, like the fabled tortoise, their strategy is to be slow and steady.
蔓生植物和攀爬植物一样 把全部的力量用于垂直生长,而不是横向生长
Vines and other climbers put all their energy into rapid vertical growth, rather than girth
尽管需要很好的对象支撑其生长
though they'll need to be well supported.
对这些蔓生植物来说,疯长是它们唯一的思想
The climbers' strategy looks chaotic but there's method in their madness.
它们的生长锥如套索般圆形移动 来寻找可以攀援的物体.
Their growing tips circle like lassoes, searching out anchors for their spindly stems.
因此向支撑的树移动时 它们会伸展而不会断裂
They put coils in their tendrils so that if their support moves, they will stretch and not snap.
在这个舞台的其他地方 第一个长满地面的就是血桐等大戟科植物
But the frontrunners at this stage, the first to fill the clearing, are pioneers like the macaranga.
它的大叶子捕捉了相当多的阳光
Their immense leaves capture huge amounts of sunlight,
所以加速了它的生长
so fueling their growth.
结果是,这种血桐一年能长8米,
As a result the macarangas grow a remarkable eight meters a year
几乎超越所有竞争者
surging ahead of almost all their rivals.
在这个长高比赛上
In the race for the top sport hundreds will start
众多的运动员中只有少数可以冲过终点
yet few will ever reach the finishing line,
大部分的植物因为缺少阳光而生长缓慢
their growth cut short by the diminishing light.
在接下来的至少4年时间里
In less than four years,
地表将暗无天日
the gap will have gone
但比赛还没有结束
but that's not the end of the race.
最后的胜利者是这些长得又稳又慢的阔叶树
The ultimate winners are the tortoises, the slow and steady hardwoods.
短命的先锋植物衰败的时候 阔叶树就取代了它们的位置
When the short lived pioneers have fallen, it's the hardwoods that take their place,
这颗50米高的树将在剩下的200年里汲取阳光
and a fifty meter giant, like this one, may keep it's place in the sun for another two hundred years.
雨林的顶部是树冠层--雨林的动力室
At the top, is the canopy, the engine room of the jungle.
在这里也可以找到大量的雨林动物
It's up here that most of the animal life in the rainforest can be found
显而易见的原因是这里有丰富的蔬果
But despite the apparent abundance of vegetable food,
尽管这样,收集食物也不容易
gathering it is seldom easy.
因为没有明显的季节变化
With no real seasons
树木全年不同时候都可以开花结果
each tree flowers or fruits at a different time of the year
食物就相当广泛了
which means that food is very widely spaced.
绢毛猴为了生存到处寻找树冠层的食物
Monkeys, like these tamarinds, must search the canopy for all kinds of food if they're to survive.
遍寻世界的雨林
but across the world's rainforests
只有一种植物一整年都会结果 无花果树
there's one type of fruiting tree that always delivers: the fig.
不管怎样 无花果树是造成生物多样性的一个重要原因
Wherever they grow, figs are a magnet for the great diversity of animals.
在亚马逊
In the Amazon,
第一个映入眼帘的是蜘蛛猴
the first to appear are the spider monkeys.
这些灵长类动物最爱吃无花果
These large primates are big fig eaters
但他们也不会轻易享受下去,还有猴子在觑觎着.
But they won't have the tree to themselves for long. Others will want a share.
这些长须蝑(也叫帝髭獠狨)也想霸占无花果树
like the diminutive emperor tamarinds.
蝑猴虽然也爱吃无花果
The tamarinds love figs too,
但因长得细小也很容易受到惊动
but being petite means they're easily scared off.
松鼠猴也很细小
Squirrel monkeys are also small
但他们以数量取胜
but they have strength in numbers.
他们在树上分享的时光可能很短 所以尽量多抓东西来吃
Their timeshare on the tree may be short, so their tactics are more smash and grab.
卷尾猴恃强凌弱
Capuchin monkeys are the bully boys in these forests
他们也来抢夺无花果
and they want the ripe figs for themselves.
无花果树是少数全年结果的树种之一
Figs are one of the few trees that fruit the year round
所以当其他食物缺乏的时候,无花果树仍然会有果实
so when other food is scarce, these fruits are always available somewhere or other.
即使对吃叶子的吼猴来说无花果实也是不能错过的,
Even for leaf eaters, like howler monkeys the ripe figs are just too good to miss.
这些大猴子就不是卷尾猴所能赶走的了
And howlers are too big for the capuchins to chase off.
无花果树非常受欢迎 甚至可以吸引多达44种的不同鸟类猴类来交替进食
Figs are so popular, that as many as 44 different kinds of bird and monkey have been seen working a shift system on a single tree.
因为结果实的树很宝贵
Because fruiting trees are so valuable,
许多猴子都有自己的领地
many monkeys are territorial
如果你居住在树顶上 那么可能没有比这种声明领土主权更好的方法了
And if you live in the treetops there's perhaps no better way of staking your claim to a territory, than this.
合趾猴通过叫声来联系公猴和母猴
The calls of the siamang gibbons begin as a duet between the dominant male and female.
家庭的其他成员也加入进来,猴群开始活跃起来
The rest of their families soon join in, and it results in a frenzy of activity.
他们的叫声超过1英里远
The calls can carry over a mile,
传递的信息也相当明确
and their message is clear.
他们在告诉其他的合趾猴邻居 这是我们的领地,非请勿进!
They tell any neighboring siamangs this is our territory. Keep out.
合趾猴通过声音广播来统治领土
Up here the calls of siamang gibbons seem to dominate the airwaves
可在雨林这个物种多样的国度里, 还可听到更多的声音.
but with the jungle's incredible diversity there are countless others trying to be heard too.
森林的每一层都有不同的曲调
Every layer seems to beat to a different tune.
在清早
In the early morning
森林合唱团特别热闹
the forest's chorus is particularly rich.
声音在冷空气中传的更远一些
Sounds travel further in the cooler air
有的叫声可以穿透密密的植被 例如这只,重低音独奏--雄红毛猩猩
But few calls can penetrate as far through the dense vegetation as this one the deep bass solo of a male orangutan.
时近中午,声音稀少, 雨林中湿热的空气也阻挡了声音的传送
In the middle of the day little stirs in the jungle and the hot dense air muffles the sound.
午后,
As the afternoon wears on,
各种声音又开始活跃起来
a different set of players begin to warm up.
昆虫鸣得很和协, 他们按照时间规律来互相传达着信息
Insects work in harmony, timing their calls to fall between the notes of others.
许多歌唱家都严格按照日程表来
Many singers stick to precise schedules
蝉很准时的在六点钟开始鸣叫
and right on cue the six o'clock cicada.
夜晚带来了新的管弦乐章
Night brings out a whole new orchestra.
刺耳的声音震耳欲聋
The cacophony of competing calls seems deafening to us
可蛙类只能听到同类的声音
but frogs ears are tuned to hear only the calls of their own kind.
蛙求爱的声音此起彼伏
The songs of courtship echo from all around.
雄性红眼叶蛙,正从树顶下落
Male gliding leaf frogs leap from the treetops.
在慢镜头下,可以看到它们用自己巨大的蹼趾控制方向 如同降落伞
To slow their descent, they use their huge webbed feet as parachutes.
这些大树蛙
These large tree frogs
大部分时间在高高的树冠层生活 只有在交配期才下来
spend most of their lives in the high canopy and only come down when it's time to breed.
站定之后,他们开始给还没出现的雌蛙唱小夜曲
Once settled, they begin to serenade their unseen females.
现在是雌蛙展开行动的时候了
Now it's time for the females to make their move.
虽然不乏众多的求爱者 可这只雌蛙已经做出了决定
There's no shortage of suitors, but this female has already made her choice.
她在朝鸣声最大的雄蛙走去, 对雌蛙来讲雄蛙叫得大声就是美
She's heading towards the loudest call, because loud calls come from big frogs and big is best,
雌蛙赶过去要注意其他小一号的雄蛙
but to reach him she must run the gauntlet of a gang of smaller suitors.
那些雄蛙的交配机会就是鬼鬼祟祟地进行偷袭.
Their only chance of mating is to make a sneaky interception.
这只雄蛙得手了
He's scored.
有更多的雌蛙正在往那边赶去
But with more females arriving all the time,
雌蛙们不会停止移动除非大雄蛙停止歌唱
it's not over until the fat frog stops singing.
脚蹼用来滑翔 也可以用来干别的事情.
Feet, so vital for gliding, are now put to other uses.
两只情侣其乐融融,三只就多有不便了.
Two's company, three's inconvenient
无论如何,雄蛙都需要用干燥的脚趾
but in any case, all male frogs are equipped with dry thumbs
如老虎钳般紧紧抓住雌蛙湿润的皮肤
which enable them to get a vice like grip on their moist partners.
先来先得
It's a case of first come first served.
在这种潮湿的环境下生活
Living in such a humid environment,
使得树蛙可以摆脱水塘的束缚
means jungle frogs are less tied to puddles and pools
因此它们无需在水中产卵
and these even lay their eggs out of water.
卵干死的几率很小
There's little chance of them drying out
在这里,也能免于被掠食者吃掉
and up here they're safer from predators.
雨林虽然不是天天下雨
Surprisingly, it doesn't rain every day in the rainforest
但是这里仍然比地球上其他地方下的多
but more still falls here than anywhere else on Earth.
平均年降水量可达2米
On average, over two meters a year.
一棵树每年可吸收几百吨的水
A single tree can suck up hundreds of tons of water each year
不过树也无法全部喝掉这些水, 多数被转换成了水蒸气从而形成了薄雾和云
But the trees can't use all this water so, much of it returns to the air as vapor, forming mist and clouds.
在亚马逊
In the Amazon,
世界上最大的原始森林
the largest unbroken stretch of rainforest in the world,
有半数的降水被树木 再次转变成云和降水并循环使用
half of all the rainwater that falls, comes from clouds produced by the trees themselves.
有这么多的降水量 世界上多数的大河都在雨林里产生也就不足为奇了
With so much rain, it's not surprising that many of the worlds largest rivers are found in rainforests.
雨林深处
Inside the forest,
十分潮湿的环境非常适合一些生命在腐殖质上生长
the high humidity creates the perfect conditions for a strange world, where life is built on decay.
象这种粘菌类变形虫正在地表上巡航 它们以细菌和地衣为生
Amoeba like slime molds cruise the surface, feeding on bacteria and rotting vegetation.
真菌类也以腐殖质为生
Fungi also flourish on decay.
这些仅仅是真菌的一个子实体
These are the fruiting bodies of the fungi,
看不见的地表下还有它的广大的菌丝网络
the only visible sign of a vast underground network of fungal filaments.
在温带森林里, 落叶形成的腐殖质层可以贮藏养分
In temperate forests, the buildup of leaf litter creates rich stores of nutrients.
可是这里不会发生这种事
That however, doesn't happen here.
土壤中的养分会被雨水冲走
Nutrients that reach the soil are leeched out by the rain
真菌用地下菌丝连接在树根上 它们很快吃掉死植物
but fungi are connected to tree roots by their underground filaments and by quickly consuming the dead
真菌因此帮助树木直接供给树木所需的矿物质
they help to recycle crucial minerals straight back into the trees.
这种生态循环的速度
And this recycling happens faster here,
比地球上其他地方要快得多
than anywhere else on the planet.
据说热带雨林里有近百万种菌类
There are thought to be nearly a million different types of fungi in the tropics.
但具体数量仍然无人知晓
The vast majority still unknown to science
一点可以确信
But one thing's for certain
没有菌类就没有雨林
without fungi, rainforests could not exist.
雨林里的一切都不能浪费
Nothing goes to waste in the rainforest.
象这种甲虫及幼虫就以菌类为食
The fungi become food for others like these beetle larvae.
幼虫寻找菌类当然比较困难 不过在父母的领引下不费吹灰之力
Finding the fungus isn't a problem for the grubs since their caring parents actually show them the way.
令人惊异的是, 地球上有80%的昆虫居住在雨林里
Incredibly, 80% of all insects live in jungles
蚂蚁是雨林昆虫中的佼佼者 每公顷可达800万只
fewer more successful than the ants. There can be 8 million individuals in a single hectare.
不过雨林是不会让它们任意逍遥的
but jungle ants don't have it all their own way.
这只子弹蚁正在现出令人担忧的症状
These bullet ants are showing some worrying symptoms.
一种叫做虫草的寄生菌的孢子
Spores from a parasitic fungus called cordyceps
已经侵入了它的身心
have infiltrated their bodies and their minds.
寄生孢子直接入侵大脑
It's infected brain directs this ant upwards
失去了方向感的子弹蚁只好用下颚咬住茎
then, utterly disorientated, it grips a stem with it's mandibles.
这些病蚁迅速被工蚁发现 并把它弄到了远离巢穴的地方
Those afflicted, that are discovered by the workers are quickly taken away and dumped far away from the colony.
这看上去有些极端,不过不是没有道理的
It seems extreme, but this is the reason why.
有几分像科幻小说
Like something out of science fiction
虫草的子实体从蚂蚁脑袋里长出来
the fruiting body of the cordyceps erupts from the ant's head.
3个星期的生长期
It can take three weeks to grow
长成后,孢子将从蚂蚁的头顶脱落
and when finished, the deadly spores will burst from it's tip
然后,附近的蚂蚁将面临死亡的威胁
then, any ant in the vicinity will be in serious risk of death.
这种剧毒的菌类足以杀死整个蚂蚁群落
The fungus is so virulent, it can wipe out whole colonies of ants
而且它们杀死的不仅仅是蚂蚁
and it's not just ants that fall victim to this killer.
大约有1千种不同的有毒寄生菌
There are literally thousands of different types of cordyceps fungi
而且它们都归属于同一物种
and remarkably, each specializes on just one species
这种攻击对雨林生物多样性起肯定作用
but these attacks do have a positive effect on the jungle's diversity.
这种寄生虫能阻止某种生物种群的优势
Since parasites like these stop any one group of animal getting the upper hand.
越多的物种产生,就会遭到越多的寄生菌攻击
The more numerous a species becomes, the more likely it'll be attacked by it's nemesis a cordyceps fungus.
在激烈的竞争环境下
With so much competition,
雨林也变成了许多非常特别的动物的家
jungles have become the home of the specialist.
这种动物在婆罗洲上是非常特别的一种
Now this animal, in the island of Borneo, is one of the most unusual.
这种会飞的"狐猴"叫做鼯猴
It's a colugo, or flying lemur,
不过它不属于狐猴,因为狐猴不会飞
though this is something of a misnomer as it doesn't actually fly and it certainly isn't a lemur
实际上很难确认它到底属于那种动物
in fact nobody's quite sure who it's closest relative is.
鼯猴靠吃嫩叶生存,
The colugo depends on a diet of young leaves
为了吃到足够的嫩叶,它必须在树与树之间移动
and to find enough of them, it must move from tree to tree.
嫩叶营养虽不丰富
The leaves are not very nutritious,
但在雨林里毫不费力就可以轻易找到
but then, getting around doesn't use much energy.
在一个晚上,鼯猴可以穿行2英里的路程
In a single night, a colugo might have to travel as far as two miles
利用它的滑翔技能完成这个任务相当简单
but that task is made easier by it's superior gliding skills.
在激烈的雨林竞争中取得胜利需要一些秘密手段
The secret of success in the competitive jungle is specializing
这让一些生物在动植物之间进化出了非常的关系
and this has led to the evolution of some very intimate relationships between plants and animals.
这是婆罗洲的猪笼草(又名捕虫草)
These are pitcher plants also from Borneo.
为了适应营养稀缺的土壤
Adapted to living in very low nutrient soils
这种象瓶子状的植物 用内侧唇瓣蜜腺分泌物来吸引昆虫
the pitcher plant gets most of it's nourishment from insects lured to nectar glands on the underside of the lids.
当昆虫被引诱过来时 光滑的内侧唇瓣使得昆虫鲜有机会逃跑
Once onboard, the waxy sides of the pitcher ensure there's little chance of escape.
多数淹死在这个水坟中...
Most slip to a watery grave.
猪笼草底部是种神秘的生化酶,帮助消化猎物
At the bottom of the pitcher glands secrete enzymes which help to digest the corpses,
给猪笼草提供养料
so feeding the plant.
但并不是所有的来访者都遭此噩运
But not all visitors have a fatal attraction to the pitchers.
红蟹蜘蛛终身生活在猪笼草里
The red crab spider spends it's entire life in the pitchers,
它们用丝线吊住自己
hanging on with threads of silk.
它直接以掉入猪笼草陷阱的虫子为生 而不用去织网
Instead of building a web, it relies on the water filled pitcher to trap it's food.
蚂蚁掉到陷阱里了 蟹蜘蛛静静等它淹死
When an ant falls in, the spider simply waits for it to drown
直接坐收渔翁之利
and then abseils down for a spot of fishing.
要生存,蚂蚁必须远离蜘蛛的魔爪
Alive, this ant would be far too dangerous for the spider to tackle
但是利用猪笼草的陷阱 意味着蟹蜘蛛照样可以美餐一顿
so, using the pitchers as traps, means it can get bigger meals
蟹蜘蛛也不全是一个不留
and the spider doesn't rob the pitcher of everything.
它也需要把战利品分一部分给猪笼草, 来给猪笼草提供营养
The digested remains of it's booty will end up in the water providing instant food for the plant.
有的食物例如蚊子幼虫在瓶底 看上去好像吃不到,不过蟹蜘蛛自有诡计
Other food, like mosquito larvae, seems to be out of reach but the spider has another sup rising trick.
它会带着一个空气泡泡
By taking it's own air supply trapped in a bubble
蟹蜘蛛可以潜入到猪笼草的底部
the crab spider can actually dive to the very bottom of the pitcher.
一旦猎物到手,蟹蜘蛛还可从水中全身而退
Once the prey is captured, the spider hauls itself back up it's silken safety line.
猪笼草好像是蟹蜘蛛的一站式商店.
The pitcher is a one stop shop for this spider,
但它并不孤独
but it's not alone.
雨林中到处都有竞争 即使在猪笼草的小小水域里
In the jungle there's competition for everything, even a small water filled pitcher plant.
雨林的特殊环境造就了生物的多样性
Such specialists create the jungle's remarkable diversity
但由于寻找食物是个巨大的挑战 因此很多雨林生物都长得很小巧
but finding enough food to survive is so challenging that most animals living here tend to be small
有一个地方是例外
though there are exceptions.
这是非洲的刚果
This is the Congo in Africa.
辽阔,原始,也是最不被探索的原始森林之一
It's a vast wilderness and the least explored of all jungles.
从这里看 这里的雨林和亚马逊及东南亚的雨林没什么两样
From up here the forest looks similar to the ones that grow in the Amazon or Southeast Asia.
但往下看,就有出人意料的发现
but down below there are some unexpected sights.
地面上有数不尽的大路和十字路口
Crisscrossing this forest, are countless miles of highways
一定是一些大家伙弄出来的
and they were made by something big.
森林象长途跋涉来寻找食物
Forest elephants roam great distances in their search for food
为了生存,它们必须隐没在幽暗的森林中
but to survive, they must emerge from the gloom of the forest.
这块空旷地 把大象从四面八方吸引过来
And clearings like this one, are a magnet for elephants from far and wide.
森林象群的个体数量 比起它的稀树草原的亲戚们要少的多
These elephants live in much smaller groups than their savanna cousins.
这可能是两个象群 一个月来第一次见面
This might be the first time that one group will have seen another for a month.
对成年雄象来说 这是摆脱孤独的大好时机
For the adult males it's a welcome break in an otherwise largely solitary existence
大象不是唯一被吸引到空旷地带的动物
and they're not the only animals attracted to the clearing.
森林水牛 红河野猪 它们也是常客
Forest buffaloes and red river hogs are also regular visitors
邦戈羚羊也是除了在空旷地很难见到的动物
as are bongos, which are very difficult to see outside these clearings.
所有的这些森林动物来到这里
All these large forest animals have come here to collect
收集埋在泥下的对身体有益的微量元素
an essential element of their diet that lies buried beneath the mud.
象鼻可以说是得到它的完美工具
And the elephant's trunk is the perfect tool for reaching it.
要找到想要的东西 大象首先要驱走覆盖着的沙土
To get what they seek the prospecting elephants must first blow away the covering layer of silt.
最终十分满意
Satisfaction at last.
它们在收集一种特殊的矿物质
They're collecting a particular kind of clay
而这种矿物质很难从自然食物中获取
that contains vital minerals scarce in their natural diet.
虽然有些牙碜 不过到了血液里也就没什么了
It may be mud, but there's just nothing quite like it for enriching the blood.
粘土也可以吸收中和吃的叶子中的毒素.
The clay also helps to absorb the toxins found in many leaves that the elephants eat.
到这里还有个好处
There are other benefits to coming here.
这块空地是唯一可以聚集 并展现象群数量的地方
These clearings are the only places where the forest elephants can get together in such numbers.
当它们返回树林时,它们将再一次分开
When they return to the forest, they will have to go their separate ways, once more.
如果说雨林中的大型动物是相当稀罕
If large animals are rare in jungles
那么群居的大型动物就更加稀罕了
then groups of large animals actually living together, are even rarer.
这些掠食者,不仅可怕, 而且还十分强大
This posse of hunters is not only formidable, it's also very large.
非洲黑猩猩不仅在地表上也在树冠层上寻找食物
In their search for food chimpanzees move effortlessly between the forest floor and the canopy.
很少有丛林动物有这样的生活方式
They're one of the few jungle animals able to do so.
无花果是黑猩猩重要的食物来源之一
Figs are a vital part of a chimpanzee's diet
这只看上去好像嘴里塞的还不够满
and some just can't seem to get enough of them.
乌干达的热带雨林有些特别
But there's something special about this stretch of forest in Uganda.
食物其实是很丰富的
Fruit is actually abundant
大量的食物养育了大量的黑猩猩
and a lot of food supports lots of chimps.
150只黑猩猩
At a hundred and fifty strong,
这个群落是迄今在非洲发现的最大的黑猩猩群落
this community of chimps is the biggest yet found in Africa.
众多的人口意味着要有广大的领土 需要很多无花果树
Their numbers are so large, that they need a big territory, lots of fig trees
也值得为它们而战
and they're willing to fight for it.
这种声音是在宣布要去搜捕侵犯领土的邻居们了
These calls announce the start of a raid into land controlled by their neighbors.
它们离开中心居住区, 巡逻队开始保持缄默行军,不时停下来倾听
As they leave their core zone, the patrol goes silent, occasionally stopping to listen.
敌人的行迹被发现并仔细检查
Signs of the enemy are detected and examined closely.
猩猩战士们已经快到达国境线了
The chimp militia are now at the very edge of their territory.
所有成员必须保持最高警惕
All need to be on maximum alert.
它们必须侧耳倾听,等待时机
Then it's wait and listen.
一个陌生的声音 引起了猩猩们的注意
An unfamiliar chimp call raises the tension.
在这个非常时刻 对手的具体数量还不知道
It's an uncertain time. The size of the rival group is as yet unknown.
就在不远处,邻居正在无花果树上进食
Not far away the neighbors are feeding in a fig tree
他们还不知道危险正在接近
oblivious to the approaching dangers.
巡逻队继续向目标进军
The patrol moves off with a sense of purpose.
在接近对手之前它们必须保持缄默
They must remain silent until they close in on their rivals.
攻击开始了!
The attack is on.
为了壮声势,它们尖叫着并击打树根冲向战场
To intimidate their opponents, the aggressors scream and drum on buttress roots.
几只公猩猩把一只母猩猩逼上绝境
Several males corner an enemy female.
面对这凶猛的攻击,这只母猩猩侥幸得以活下来
It's a ferocious attack, and she's lucky to escape with her life.
另外一些就不那么走运了
Others are not so fortunate.
战斗胜利,出现了一个可怕的场景
The battle won, a grizzly scene unfolds.
敌人的孩童被抓住并被杀死
An enemy youngster has been caught and killed.
并被这群黑猩猩吃掉
The carcass is shared between members of the group, and eaten.
捕杀敌人虽然有利于保证自己的食物供给
Killing a competitor makes sense if you want to protect your food supply
但是还搞不清楚它们究竟为什么要吃同类
but exactly why they cannibalize the dead chimp, is not fully understood.
也可能是为了获得额外的蛋白质吧
It may simply be a chance for some extra protein.
团队合作使这群黑猩猩取得巨大成功
Teamwork has brought this group of chimps great success
但是它们很快将盛极而衰
but they'll soon reach the limits of their power.
雨林中激烈的资源竞争 使得没有哪个物种可以统治这块地方
The competition for resources ensures that no one species dominates the jungle.
雨林的物种多样性正在消失 而雨林却是维持地球生态系统微妙平衡的关键
The rainforest's great diversity has come at a cost. It has made them the most finely balanced ecosystems in the world
大肆破坏雨林最终伤害到的另一种伟大猿类 就是黑猩猩的近亲--我们人类自己
only too easily upset and destroyed by that other great ape the chimpanzee's closest relative -- Ourselves.